Guide to the Lewis B. Cullman Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Lewis B. Cullman papers
1947-2017
MS 2072
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
4.63
(18 boxes)
The collection documents the business and philanthropic activities of Lewis B. Cullman. Business records include business dealings with the Allied Graphic Arts Company and Cullman's leveraged buyout of the Orkin Exterminating Company in the 1960s. Also included are two bound volumes documenting the merger of Cullman's company, Cullman Ventures, Inc., with Mead Acquisition Corporation in 1999. Personal papers include biographical information, documents relating to Cullman's relationship with Yale University, records of his philanthropic contributions to New York institutions, and publicity materials for organizations which Cullman founded or contributed to. The collection also includes audiovisual recordings documenting programs funded by Cullman, interviews, and publicity materials about Cullman and his charitable contributions. There are also photographs of Cullman taken at organizations and events related to his philanthropy.
Cullman, Lewis B., 1919-
Biographical / Historical
Lewis B. Cullman is a New York City businessman and philanthropist. Born in 1919, Cullman received a BA from Yale and a master's degree in meteorology from New York University. In his business career, Cullman served as the chief executive of the At-A-Glance calendar and appointment-book company, and in 1964 engineered the purchase of the Orkin Exterminating Company. After selling his company in 1999, Cullman became a philanthropist. He serves on the boards of the New York Public Library, the Museum of Modern Art, and the New York Botanical Garden. He is also involved with Chess in the Schools, a program which teaches chess to New York Public School students, and is the founder of the Cullman Child Development Center, in Sidney, NY. Cullman was thrice married, most recently in 2010 to Louise Hirschfeld. His second wife, Dorothy, played a large role in his philanthropic activites.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged in three groupings: Business records, Personal papers, and Photographs.
Scope and Contents
The collection documents the business and philanthropic activities of Lewis B. Cullman. Business records include business dealings with the Allied Graphic Arts Company and Cullman's leveraged buyout of the Orkin Exterminating Company in the 1960s. Also included are two bound volumes documenting the merger of Cullman's company, Cullman Ventures, Inc., with Mead Acquisition Corporation in 1999. Personal papers include biographical information, documents relating to Cullman's relationship with Yale University, records of his philanthropic contributions to New York institutions, and publicity materials for organizations which Cullman founded or contributed to. The collection also includes audiovisual recordings documenting programs funded by Cullman, interviews, and publicity materials about Cullman and his charitable contributions. There are also photographs of Cullman taken at organizations and events related to his philanthropy.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy of non-commercially produced items for their personal use should consult the ordering reproductions information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
Original born digital files, as well as preservation masters, may not be accessed due to their fragility. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist request that they be made. Born digital files cannot be accessed remotely. System requirements include a Manuscripts and Archives computer and file viewing software.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Lewis B. Cullman, 2017
Publicity; Consolidation and merger of corporations -- United States; Charity organization; Cullman, Lewis B., 1919-; Cullman, Lewis B., 1919-; Science, Industry and Business Library (New York Public Library); New York Public Library for the Performing Arts; New York Botanical Garden
- Business records
  - Allied Graphic Arts, 1966-1975 (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
  - LBC Incubation, 1962-1972 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
  - Orkin deal, 1964-1968 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Merger of Cullman Ventures, Inc. and Mead Acquisition Corp. Volume 1, 1999-11-01 (Box 2)
  - Merger of Cullman Ventures, Inc. and Mead Acquisition Corp. Volume 2, 1999-11-01 (Box 3)
- Personal papers
  - Yale University files, circa 1969 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Biographical, 1976-2017 (Box 4, Folder 2-5)
  - Philanthropy, 1992-2016
    - Philanthropy files, 1992-2016 (Box 4, Folder 6-8)
    - Recordings of programs funded by Cullman
      Conditions Governing Access
      Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy of non-commercially produced items for their personal use should consult the ordering reproductions information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
      - City Arts, 1995-04-10; 1 (Box 7)
      - City Arts, 1999-01-22; 1 (Box 8)
      - City Arts, 1999-01-29; 1 (Box 9)
      - City Arts, 1999-02-05; 1 (Box 10)
      - City Arts, 1999-02-12; 1 (Box 11)
      - City Arts, 1999-03-26; 1 (Box 12)
  - Publicity, 1947-1992
    - Publicity files, 1947-1992 (Box 4, Folder 9-12)
    - Publicity audiovisual recordings
      The computer files are unprocessed and may contain sensitive information or be in a physical state that would prohibit use. Researchers wishing to request access should email mssa.assist@yale.edu. The request should outline the scope and purpose of the research project, why the researcher believes the material is relevant to their project, and contact information. If possible the request should also include a list of specific material of interest including collection, box, and folder numbers (or folder descriptions if folders are not numbered). The review may take several weeks.
      - Cullman Child Development Center Dedication Ceremony, 1992-05-18; 1 (Box 13)
      - Unforgettable: A tribute from the employees of the At-A-Glance Group in recognition of Mr. Cullman's many contributions during his twenty-one years of ownership, 1999-11-09; 1 (Box 14)
      - New York Science, Industry and Business Library (SIBL), Experience, 2003; 1 (Box 15)
      - Setting the Stage: Interviews with Bill Baker, 2007-02-20; 1 (Box 16)
      - Good Day New York, Out of Doors- Lincoln Center, circa 2000; 1 (Box 17)
      - Chess in the Schools: The Power in Small Moves, circa 2010; 2017-M-0058-0001; 1 (Box 18)
      - The New York Botanical Garden: Look Who's Minding Our Planet, 2016-08; 2017-M-0058-0002; 1 (Box 18)
      - Lewis and Dorothy Cullman talk about charity (Library for the Performing Arts), circa 2000s; 2017-M-0058-0003; 1 (Box 18)
      - Lewis B. Cullman: Can't take it with you, 2004; 2017-M-0058-0004; 1 (Box 18)
  - Awards and recognition, 1998-2017 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 2003 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Photographs
  - General, 2009-2015 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Chess in the Schools, 2003 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Cullman Child Development Center, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - New York Botanical Garden, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Portraits, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Yale Dedication, Cullman Courts, 2008 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Edgar, Arthur, Lewis, and Joseph Cullman, circa 1970 (Box 6, Folder 1)